Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Rufus Henry Fitzgerald, Administrative Files, 1945-1955 UA.2.10.1945-1955
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Rufus Henry Fitzgerald, Administrative Files
1937-1960
1945-1955
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor
UA.2.10.1945-1955
34.3 Linear Feet (61 boxes)
CONTENT WARNING -- This finding aid contains records that have been identified as including offensive, harmful, racist, or misrepresentative creator supplied language. In keeping with archival best practice, this language has been retained to preserve the context of the records. In keeping but acknowledging this language, A&SC hopes to encourage critical assessment and questioning of historical materials. Researchers should bear this in mind when accessing. This is a collection of the office files of University of Pittsburgh Chancellor Rufus H. Fitzgerald (1945-1955). In addition to the day to day files, there are those that document the construction of several large buildings on campus as well as the development of the Medical Center.
Folder 386 in Box 59 and Folder 389 in Box 60 have been deleted from the inventory. There is no indication that material is missing and may just have been an error or consolidation.
Acquisition Information
These files were deposited at the Archives Service Center from storage on May 6, 1969.
Access Restrictions
The Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Scholarships in Boxes 40-45 are restricted.
Biography
Rufus Henry Fitzgerald was the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh from 1945 until his retirement in July of 1955. He previously held the positions of Provost (1938-1942) and Vice-Chancellor (1942-1945). He came to Pittsburgh after having been a director and professor of the Fine Arts Department at the State University of Iowa.
During his tenure, he guided the construction projects of the Nurses Residence, the Fitzgerald Field House, Clapp Hall, Engineering Building, and the groundbreaking for the School of Health Professions. He integrated the Schools of Pharmacy, Retailing and Public Health into the University and grew the endowment from $3.5 million to $29 million.
Fitzgerald, a native of Pelham, North Carolina, received his Bachelors degree from Guilford College in 1911 and a Master of Fine Arts from the University of Tennessee in 1919. He was married to Damie Cornell until her death in 1963 then married Elizabeth Hays, who was his wife at the time of his death on April 11, 1966. He and Damie had two daughters, Helen Bethel and Mildred Brownlee.
Arrangement
This collection was left in its original, mostly alphabetic, order.
Previous Citation
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Rufus Henry Fitzgerald, Administrative Files, 1945-1955, UA.2.10.1945-1955, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
This is a collection of the office files of University of Pittsburgh Chancellor Rufus H. Fitzgerald (1945-1955). In addition to the day to day files, there are those that document the construction of several of the University's significant buildings on campus as well as the development of the Medical Center. In addition to the University's records, there are also files that document Fitzgerald's involvement with the City of Pittsburgh, the State of Pennsylvania, and the University's role with the G.I. Bill and the influx of students that resulted.
Separated Material
Folders 45-48 from Box 6 called Building Program were moved to Folders 648-649 in Box 79 of Chancellor Litchfields's files, UA RG 2/10 1956-1965.
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Administration; Health and medicine; Correspondence; Administrative records; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; University of Pittsburgh; Fitzgerald, Rufus Henry; University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor; University of Pittsburgh
- Admissions, 1941-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Committee meeting minutes from Fitzgerald's time as Vice Chancellor as well as Chancellor.
- Allegheny Observatory, 1941-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Alumni, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Headquarters in Attorney Charles J. Margiotti home on Bigelow Boulevard – to be torn down in future for expansion (part of land deal acquired by the Scaife and two Mellon Foundations for use of the University (1954); Fund raising; Smorgasbord
- American Association of University Professors, 1940-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Glenna Walter Mars tenure material (also in Nursing file) 1954; Reports of various AAUP Committees; 1939-53; Blacklisting, Academic Freedom and Tenure.
- American Council on Education, August 1940-June 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Wartime research; Impact of War on University; Selective service system
- American Council on Education, July 1946- June 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- American Council of Education, July 1946-June 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Study of disabled veterans in colleges and universities, 1946/47; Cost of training in psychiatric social work, clinical psychology, nursing, 1947.
- American Council of Education, July 1948-June 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Report on Scientist's Resources Project, Contract N7onr-22 with the American Council on Education
- American Council on Education, July 1949-June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Federal Scholarships and Fellowship Programs, 1949
- American Council on Education, July 1950-June 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Higher education and national defense
- American Council on Education, July 1951-June 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Athletic policies in American universities; 1951, questionnaire for 6th ed. of American University & Colleges
- American Council on Education, July 1952-June 1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  G.I. Bill for veterans on active duty on or after June 27, 1950-Revision of basis of payment under Public Law 550
- Applications, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Applied Social Sciences, School of, 1938-June 1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Reports, History, Correspondence
- Applied Social Sciences, School of, July 1943-June 1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Design for further development, 1945-50; Report to Advisory Committee; Recommendation for degree of Doctor of Social Administration
- Association of American Colleges, 1938-June 1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Association of American Colleges, July 1947-July 1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Manual of corporate giving; Declaration of manpower, Association of American Colleges annual meeting, January 10, 1951
- Association of Urban Universities, November 1941-June 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Role of religion in the urban university; a Yale study on religion in higher education, 1946; The significance of the Pittsburgh story, and address by Arthur B. Van Buskirk, November 1954; Association of Urban Universities Resolutions; Pittsburgh renaissance; a special magazine of the Pittsburgh Press, December 13, 1953
- Athletics, December 1945-June 1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Trip to inspect facilities at University of Wisconsin & University of Michigan – Deans of the College, Business and Administration; Facsimile of contract offered to Captain Thomas Hamilton, 1949; Athletic Committee Meeting, 1949; Use of stadium by Civic Light Opera, 1949-50; Meeting on organization for physical education and intercollegiate athletics, October 1949; Snapshots of groups on the trips to visit other universities; Tom Hamilton becomes the Director of Athletics; Hamilton's biographical listing; also handwritten letter, September 8, 1948; Freshman football field at Ellsworth Center, Minutes
- Athletics, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Correspondence on the "Athletic Situation"
- Athletics, July 1, 1951-June 30, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Memo on proposed conference (Penn State, Notre Dame, and Pitt) 1954; Tom Hamilton as Head; Minutes of Athletic Committee, 1953; Eastern College Athletic Conference code – Athletics, Policies and principles governing financial aid to students at the University of Pittsburgh, 1952, Department of Physical Education (program); Michelosen for Pitt Committee; Dedication of the Field House on December 15, 1951 (speech)
- Athletics, July 1, 1954-May 1955 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Policies and principles governing financial aid to students, 1955; Resolution of Senate of Pennsylvania re collegiate sports events on television, 1955; Brochure: Physical Education Plant for the University of Pittsburgh (requested from the State); Letter asking for expansion of physical education facilities
- Athletics Investigation (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Recent statement or actions concerning Conference rules and regulations, 1945-1946; Handbook of the Intercollegiate Conference of Faculty representatives. Rev. 1941; Eastern Conference Athletic Conference – application for membership; Study of Athletic situation; Report of the Faculty Committee
- Athletics, Committee on Athletic Policy (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Code for the conduct of athletics at the University of Pittsburgh; Seeking Head Football Coach; Letters of application for; Letter by Clark D. Shaunessy concerning policy at Pitt
- A General (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Activities; Allen, Harvey; American Chemical Society; American Friends of Hebrew University; Anathan, Appointments; Arensberg; Argonne; Art Institute, Avinoff
- Band, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Charles Rickmond and the admission of Black Students to the Band.
- Board of Public Education (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Proposal for a new educational unit in the University; Admitting High School Students after two years; Map of Pittsburgh showing all public school locations & main thoroughfares (Dec. 1941)
- Board of Trustees, 1939-1949 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Investigating Committee of the Board; Report of the Legislative Committee...Resolution 61; Standing Committees for 1948-49
- Board of Trustees, 1943-June 1946 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  George H. Clapp – biography; and a letter; List of Board members; A Plan for Alumni representation on the Board; After World War II, Appreciation of Faculty who have signed (4 pages) for service rendered during war
- Board of Trustees, July 1946-June 1947 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Enrollment; Retirement Annuity; Buildings; Mellon, Falk and Scaife correspondence
- Board of Trustees, July 1947-June 1948 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Financials; Enrollment report; Sutherland memorial, School of Medicine; Members and Standing Committees, Correspondence
- Board of Trustees, June 1948-June1951 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  Letters concerning acquiring property on DeSoto Street, 1951; Letters concerning Science Building (Falk, Bowman, Scaife); Biography (Samuel Alfred Taylor) after death – B.S. degree in 1887; Letter from Hugh Thomson Kerr to Dr. Fitzgerald; Resolution adopted in memoriam, George Hubbard Clapp, 1949; Women's Hospital of Pittsburgh agreement with University of Pittsburgh; Alan M. Scaife received the Benjamin Rush Award, 1948; Professor Marian Hathaway and Communism controversy; State offer to Pitt for management of WPIC. 1945-55 Agreement with Women's Hospital
- Board of Trustees, July 1951-June 1955 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  List of persons invited to the Trustees' Dinner honoring Chancellor and Mrs. Fitzgerald; Programs for evening; Roy C. McKenna received 20 year pin as Trustee – Dr. Fitzgerald presented it; Lists of those attending Trustees dinner before meetings; (clipping) May 23, 1954 "Business and the public must be good neighbors" philosophy of Richard K. Mellon; Plan to develop Engineering and Mines; Correspondence concerning "College Self-Study Committee"; clippings concerning Cathedral Lawn
- Board of Trustees, Chancellor Search Committee, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Board of Trustees, Finance Committee, 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Board of Trustees, Property Committee (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Board of Trustees (Box 5, Folder 37)
  Correspondence: A.M. Scaife
- John Gabbert Bowman (Box 6, Folder 38)
  Memos on management of university; Speech: The necessity of music, 1935; Urged to put in tenure for faculty
- John Gabbert Bowman (Box 6, Folder 39)
  Newspaper clipping, 19544; How to honor him, by R.H. Fitzgerald; Honorary degrees in 1948 to Chancellor Bowman and Sir Richard Livingston; "Former Pitt Chancellor's estate in Bedford – Bowman sale to State aired" (clipping, 1951); "Pittsburgh, city of courage", by John G. Bowman
- Brackenridge Portraits (Box 6, Folder 40)
  Purchased from Joseph McKibben, of St. Paul, Minnesota on December 20, 1938; description of the portrait of Hugh Henry Brackenridge; description of portrait of Sabina Wolfe Brackenridge, by Rembrandt Peale; Portraits paid for by Dr. George Hubbard Clapp, President of the Board of Trustees
- Brookings Institution (Box 6, Folder 41)
  Seminar held at the University of Pittsburgh, 1951
- Buhl Foundation (Box 6, Folder 42)
  New Grant of $82,500 – scholarship aid for 3 years; Annual report from Research Project in chemistry, physics, and biology, 1939/40
- Buhl Planetarium (Box 6, Folder 43)
  Science Quiz Program, 1954
- Building Program (Box 6, Folder 44-48)
  Separated Material
  Folders 45-48 were moved to Litchfield's files: 2/10 1956-1965 Box 79 Folders 648-649.
- Building Program, Clapp Hall (Box 7, Folder 49)
  Science Building: George Hubbard Clapp Hall; Donations from the Buhl Foundation
- Building Program, Clapp Hall (Box 7, Folder 50)
  Groundbreaking ceremony July 1,1954; Luncheon and program, speech by C. Glen King.
- Building Program, Clapp Hall (Box 7, Folder 51)
  Report to the Buhl Foundation on Research in the Natural Sciences…with reference to Clapp Hall, April 1949
- Building Program, Planning and Development Committee of the Board of Trustees (Box 7, Folder 52)
- Building Program, 1949-1957 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  Contributions
- Building Program, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  Correspondence
- Building Program, June 3, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  Fundraising Dinner June 3, 1948; Speech by Rufus H. Fitzgerald and Alan Scaife; Guest list
- Building Program, Dormitories, 1949-1955 (Box 8, Folder 56)
- Building Program: Eggers and Higgins, Architects for Clapp Hall (Box 8, Folder 57)
- Building Program, Engineering (Box 8, Folder 58)
  Clipping about gift or the Bevier Library in the Engineering Building; Architects; budget; Board of Trustees authorization; Action from Trustees to order necessary furniture; Dean Fitterer had to approve all installations; drawings of floor plans; Plans for dedication of the Bevier Library; (no ground-breaking ceremony for Engineering Building); Program for development by Trustees Committee for Engineering; Early plan to add to State Hall and a wing to Alumni instead of a new building; Proposal for development and improvement of the Schools
- Building Program, Medical Center, 1947-1949 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  Correspondence with Leon Falk
- Building Program, Field House, 1946-1952 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  Blue print; ground-breaking ceremony February 2, 1949; Lists of guests for ceremony; Meetings on construction of the field house
- Building Program, Field House (Box 8, Folder 61)
  Alternate plan
- Building Program, Fifth and Craig (Box 8, Folder 62)
- Building Program, First Boston Corporation, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  Correspondence on investments and construction financing.
- Building Program, Medical Offices and Garage, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 64)
- Building Program, Proposed Gymnasium (Box 9, Folder 66)
- Building Program, Emery B. Jackson (Box 9, Folder 67)
  Medical & Nursing buildings; Reports to Alan M. Scaife
- Building Program Fundraising, 1948-1955 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  Ketchum contracted to conduct the campaign, Medical Center, Nursing, Gymnasium, Science Building, Library
- Building Program Brochures, 1948-1950 (Box 9, Folder 68b)
  Brochures describe the physical and academic aspects of the University circa 1950. The large untitled brochure includes am image of Storm Jameson with students, Library reading room in the Cathedral and the Pathology Laboratory in Pennsylvania Hall as well as campus maps with proposed buildings. The brochure titled "Education lights the way" has descriptions of Pitt's academic programs and their interaction with industry. Included are numbers of enrolled students from local business and industry.
- Building Program, Library, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  Includes drawing of cathedral grounds where library would be situated, a report on the Pitt Library by Ellsworth, Director of Libraries at Iowa, a 1949 issue of the Harvard Crimson describing the Lamont Library
- Building Program, Logan Armory (Box 9, Folder 70)
  Moved to 2/10 1956-65 FF 275
- Building Program: Medical Building, June 28, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  Ground Breaking Ceremony; photographs moved to media files (Buildings-Scaife)
- Building Program, Medical Building, Sub-contracts (Box 9, Folder 72)
  Scaife Hall
- Building Program, Medical Building, Schools of the Health Professions (Box 9, Folder 73)
  Clippings; plans for building; fire in the building; plans for a parking garage; Memorials: Main library by Maurice and Laura Falk Foundation, Graduate Laboratory for Physiological Chemistry, by Wherrett Memorial Laboratory, Departmental library for anatomy, by the Rea family
- Building Program: Medical Center campaign, 1953-1958 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  Campaign report to subscribers, 1954-55; List of prospective donors; Reports on the progress of the buildings, etc.; TV program by Dr. Moore being interviewed by Dr. Albert Martin concerning the Health program; Statement for the Richard King Mellon Foundation for the University of Pittsburgh Health Center, 1953
- Building Program: Medical Center campaign, 1953-1958 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  Subscriptions; Building Fund progress report, February 1952; Memos concerning the campaign and speakers: Memos of Conferences in Chancellor's office; Estimates of cost
- Building Program, Medical Center campaign (Box 9, Folder 75b)
- Building Program, Medical Center campaign, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 76)
- Building Program, Medical Center campaign (Box 9, Folder 76b)
- Building Program, Medical Center (Box 9, Folder 77)
  Publicity materials
- Building Program, Medical Center (Box 11, Folder 78)
  Proposed center's architectural drawings, plans, renderings along with correspondence
- Building Program, Medical Center campaign (Box 11, Folder 79)
  Campaign announcement dinner 1/18/1954; Letters; addresses in acknowledgement of the presentation of endowment grants by A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust, Richard King Mellon Foundation, Sarah Mellon Scaife Foundation (book); guest list at dinner; invitations; clippings; President Eisenhower's letter of congratulations; Letters of congratulations
- Building Program, Medical Center campaign (Box 11, Folder 79b)
- Building Program, School of Medicine, November 18, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 80)
  Report of Committee on Research and Development
- Building Program, A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust, 1952-1954 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  Special purchase of property; List of properties acquired,1954; Land for Graduate School of Public Health
- Building Program, General and Miscellaneous, 1947-1955 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  Upper Campus PA Hall, Upper Dental Building, Old Mellon Inst. Ellsworth Center for Engineering and Physical Science, Buildings in progress 1954; some Planning and Development Committee materials
- Building Program, Natural Sciences Building (Clapp Hall), 1957 (Box 12, Folder 83)
  List of facilities and departments for Clapp Hall.
- Building Program, newspaper publicity, 1948, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 84)
- Building Program, proposed financing, 1950-1955 (Box 12, Folder 85)
  New York Life and Mellon Bank
- Building Program, Nurse's Residence, 1949-1953 (Box 12, Folder 86-86a)
  Budget; plans; builder, statement of policy for residence; correspondence with the Treasurer; memorials for the residence (lists); inspected by General State Authority, September 23, 1952; Report of Building Fund; Program for Ground Breaking exercises, October 12, 1950; Plans for merger of Nurses' Home with the University of Pittsburgh, 1948
- Building Program, Oakland Expansion, 1952-1959 (Box 12, Folder 87-87a)
  Urban redevelopment authority, Areas 7 and 8, Children's Hospital, Proposed relocation of Forbes Avenue; Development for athletic purposes; Development for Public Health Area; Logan Armory discussion; Acreage donated to hospitals and Veteran's Administration Hospital; List of needs of the University; List of floors and occupants in the Cathedral of Learning; Blueprint of proposed armory
- Building Program, Oakland Planning Committee, 1949-1951 (Box 13, Folder 88)
  Oakland study, 1950, findings and recommendations; Summary of recommendations, 1951; Oakland study, 950; Interim report of the Oakland Civic Center Study, 1950
- Building Program, Landscaping and Planning, 1949-1951 (Box 13, Folder 89)
  Olmstead Brothers correspondence
- Building Program, Parking (Box 13, Folder 90)
  Medical Center, Public Health, Parking committee
- Building Program, funding sources (Box 13, Folder 91)
  Federal and State sources of funds and HilliBurton Act for Hospitals
- Building Program, Graduate School of Pubic Health (Box 13, Folder 92)
  Costs, opening, Library furniture; Selection of contractor; Municipal Hospital building
- Building Program, Financial considerations (Box 13, Folder 93)
  G.S.Rupp, Board of Trustees, Letter dated 1924 from Clapp to Chancellor Bowman re: his chancellorship
- Building Program, Financial considerations, 1948-1955 (Box 14, Folder 94)
  Correspondence with A.M. Scaife; Gifts, $300,000 & 206,000 in 1954; $3 million; Building Fund campaign and solicitations; School of Medicine; Nurses Home; Field House
- Building Program, Schenley Apartments, 1956-1960 (Box 14, Folder 95)
  Allocation of space to students, 1960 (Litchfield); minutes of Administrative Subcommittee concerning plans for Building G; Amount needed to purchase; Plans for alterations; Purchase of; Form of agreement for purchase of Schenley Apartments with the Bellefield Company; Report of Operations (1954); Appraisal
- Building Program, Schenley Hotel and Apartments (Box 14, Folder 96)
  Plans and estimates for the Student Union and Dormitories; Lists of rooms, baths, etc.; Summary of estimates for alterations; How to best use spaces in Schenley Apartments; Opening of Brackenridge Hall
- Building Program, Medical Center, 1948-1953 (Box 14, Folder 97)
  Schmidt, Garden & Erikson Architects; DeSoto & Terrace Street planning; Nursing, Medicine; Medical Center, Blueprints
- Building Program, Student Union, 1949-1955 (Box 14, Folder 98)
  Michael Hare (architect); Estimates for core drilling for Student Center Gymnasium; Blueprints
- Building Program, Town Hall Site, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  Langley Hall and Masonic Temple
- Building Program, Science Building and Student Center, 1948-1954 (Box 14, Folder 100)
  Correspondence Trautwein & Howard (architects); Gymnasium, Student Center and Science building; Sample agreement
- Building Program, University Recreation Center, 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  Wildwood property; formerly Hubbard Reservation; Purchased for University by Mrs. Scaife; Plans for membership and fees; Site plan of Wildwood
- Buildings and Grounds, 1947, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 102)
  Duties and responsibilities of members of the Buildings & Grounds staff; correspondence concerning a survey and report on the department
- Bureau of Business Research, 1948-1955 (Box 15, Folder 103)
  Subject of an electronic computer brought up by Chancellor Fitzgerald; Grant by M. & L. Falk Foundation for a study of changes in the structure of manufacturing costs, 1899-1939
- Business Administration, School of, 1947-1954 (Box 15, Folder 104)